<!DOCTYPE bookinfo PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN' 'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'><bookinfo>

  <othercredit role='proofreader'>
    <firstname>FIX</firstname>
    <surname>ME!</surname>
  </othercredit>
  <othercredit role='interiordesigner'>
    <firstname>David</firstname>
    <surname>Futato</surname>
  </othercredit>
  <othercredit role='illustrator'>
    <firstname>Robert</firstname>
    <surname>Romano</surname>
  </othercredit>
  <othercredit role='coverdesigner'>
    <firstname>Karen</firstname>
    <surname>Montgomery</surname>
  </othercredit>

  <!-- All rights reserved. -->
  <publisher>
    <publishername>O&#x2019;Reilly Media, Inc.    </publishername>
    <address format='linespecific'>
      <street>1005 Gravenstein Highway North</street>
      <city>Sebastopol</city>
      <state>CA</state>
      <postcode>95472</postcode>
    </address>
  </publisher>

  <legalnotice role='printlocation'>
    <para>Printed in the United States of America.</para>
  </legalnotice>

  <legalnotice role='printer'>
    <para>[?]</para>
  </legalnotice>

  <legalnotice role='use'>
    <para>O&#x2019;Reilly books may be purchased for educational, business, or sales promotional use. Online editions are also available for most 
          titles (<ulink role='orm:hideurl:ital' url='http://my.safaribooksonline.com/?portal=oreilly'>http://my.safaribooksonline.com</ulink>). For more information, contact our corporate/institutional sales department:
          800-998-9938 or <phrase role='keep-together'><email>corporate@oreilly.com</email></phrase>.</para>
  </legalnotice>

  <legalnotice role='trademarks'>
    <para>Nutshell Handbook, the Nutshell Handbook logo, and the O&#x2019;Reilly logo
          are registered trademarks of O&#x2019;Reilly Media, Inc. !!FILL THIS IN!!
          and related trade dress are trademarks of O&#x2019;Reilly Media, Inc.    </para>
    <para>Many of the designations used by manufacturers and sellers to distinguish
          their products are claimed as trademarks. Where those designations appear
          in this book, and O&#x2019;Reilly Media, Inc., was aware of a trademark claim,
          the designations have been printed in caps or initial caps.    </para>
  </legalnotice>

  <legalnotice role='damages'>
    <para>While every precaution has been taken in the preparation of this book,
        the publisher and authors assume no responsibility for errors or omissions, 
        or for damages resulting from the use of the information contained herein.</para>
  </legalnotice>
<isbn>9781449323912</isbn><edition>1</edition><author><firstname>Yaron</firstname><surname>Minsky</surname><authorblurb><para>Yaron Minsky heads the Technology group at Jane Street, a proprietary trading firm that is the largest industrial user of OCaml. He was responsible for introducing OCaml to the company and for managing the company&apos;s transition to using OCaml for all of its core infrastructure. Today, billions of dollars worth of securities transactions flow each day through those systems. Yaron obtained his PhD in Computer Science from Cornell University, where he studied distributed systems. Yaron has lectured, blogged and written about OCaml for years, with articles published in Communications of the ACM and the Journal of Functional Programming. He chairs the steering committee of the Commercial Users of Functional Programming, and is a member of the steering committee for the International Conference on Functional Programming.</para></authorblurb></author><author><firstname>Anil</firstname><surname>Madhavapeddy</surname><authorblurb><para>Anil Madhavapeddy is a Senior Research Fellow at the University of Cambridge, based in the Systems Research Group. He was on the original team that developed the Xen hypervisor, and helped develop an industry-leading cloud management toolstack written entirely in OCaml. This XenServer product has been deployed on hundreds of thousands of physical hosts, and drives critical infrastructure for many Fortune 500 companies. Prior to obtaining his PhD in 2006 from the University of Cambridge, Anil had a diverse background in industry at Network Appliance, NASA and Internet Vision. In addition to professional and academic activities, he is an active member of the open-source development community with the OpenBSD operating system, is co-chair of the Commercial Uses of Functional Programming
workshop, and serves on the boards of startup companies such as Ashima Arts where OCaml is extensively used.</para></authorblurb></author><author><firstname>Jason</firstname><surname>Hickey</surname><authorblurb><para>Jason Hickey is a Software Engineer at Google Inc. in Mountain View, California. He is part of the team that designs and develops the global computing infrastructure used to support Google services, including the software systems for managing and scheduling massively distributed computing resources. Prior to joining Google, Jason was an Assistant Professor of Computer Science at Caltech, where his research was in reliable and fault-tolerant computing systems, including programming language design, formal methods, compilers, and new models of distributed computation. He obtained his PhD in Computer Science from Cornell University, where he studied programming languages. He is the author of the MetaPRL system, a logical framework for design and analysis of large software systems; OMake, an advanced build system for large software projects. He is the author of the textbook, An Introduction to Objective Caml (unpublished).</para></authorblurb></author><editor><firstname>Mike</firstname><surname>Loukides</surname></editor><editor><firstname>Andy</firstname><surname>Oram</surname></editor><copyright><year>2010</year><holder>Jason Hickey, Anil Madhavapeddy, Yaron Minsky</holder></copyright><editor role='production'><firstname>Chris</firstname><surname>Hearse</surname></editor><editor role='copy'><firstname/><surname/></editor><othercredit role='indexer'><firstname/><surname/></othercredit><printhistory><formalpara><title>First Edition</title><para>December, 2013</para></formalpara></printhistory><revhistory><revision><date>YYYY-MM-DD</date><revremark>First release</revremark></revision></revhistory><legalnotice role='perfect'><para></para></legalnotice></bookinfo>
