<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<preface id="preface">
  <title>Preface</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>Conventions Used in This Book</title>

    <para>The following typographical conventions are used in this
    book:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis>Italic</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Indicates new terms, URLs, email addresses, filenames, and
          file extensions.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><literal>Constant width</literal></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Used for program listings, as well as within paragraphs to
          refer to program elements such as variable or function names,
          databases, data types, environment variables, statements, and
          keywords.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><userinput>Constant width bold</userinput></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Shows commands or other text that should be typed literally by
          the user.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><replaceable>Constant width italic</replaceable></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Shows text that should be replaced with user-supplied values
          or by values determined by context.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <tip>
      <para>This icon signifies a tip, suggestion, or general note.</para>
    </tip>

    <caution>
      <para>This icon indicates a warning or caution.</para>
    </caution>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Using Code Examples</title>

    <para>This book is here to help you get your job done. In general, you may
    use the code in this book in your programs and documentation. You do not
    need to contact us for permission unless you’re reproducing a significant
    portion of the code. For example, writing a program that uses several
    chunks of code from this book does not require permission. Selling or
    distributing a CD-ROM of examples from O’Reilly books does require
    permission. Answering a question by citing this book and quoting example
    code does not require permission. Incorporating a significant amount of
    example code from this book into your product’s documentation does require
    permission.</para>

    <para>We appreciate, but do not require, attribution. An attribution
    usually includes the title, author, publisher, and ISBN. For example:
    “<emphasis>Book Title</emphasis> by Some Author (O’Reilly). Copyright 2012
    Some Copyright Holder, 978-0-596-xxxx-x.”</para>

    <para>If you feel your use of code examples falls outside fair use or the
    permission given above, feel free to contact us at
    <email>permissions@oreilly.com</email>.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Safari® Books Online</title>

    <note role="safarienabled">
      <para>Safari Books Online (<ulink role="orm:hideurl:ital"
      url="http://my.safaribooksonline.com/?portal=oreilly">www.safaribooksonline.com</ulink>)
      is an on-demand digital library that delivers expert <ulink
      role="orm:hideurl"
      url="http://www.safaribooksonline.com/content">content</ulink> in both
      book and video form from the world’s leading authors in technology and
      business. Technology professionals, software developers, web designers,
      and business and creative professionals use Safari Books Online as their
      primary resource for research, problem solving, learning, and
      certification training.</para>
    </note>

    <para>Safari Books Online offers a range of <ulink role="orm:hideurl"
    url="http://www.safaribooksonline.com/subscriptions">product mixes</ulink>
    and pricing programs for <ulink role="orm:hideurl"
    url="http://www.safaribooksonline.com/organizations-teams">organizations</ulink>,
    <ulink role="orm:hideurl"
    url="http://www.safaribooksonline.com/government">government
    agencies</ulink>, and <ulink role="orm:hideurl"
    url="http://www.safaribooksonline.com/individuals">individuals</ulink>.
    Subscribers have access to thousands of books, training videos, and
    prepublication manuscripts in one fully searchable database from
    publishers like O’Reilly Media, Prentice Hall Professional, Addison-Wesley
    Professional, Microsoft Press, Sams, Que, Peachpit Press, Focal Press,
    Cisco Press, John Wiley &amp; Sons, Syngress, Morgan Kaufmann, IBM
    Redbooks, Packt, Adobe Press, FT Press, Apress, Manning, New Riders,
    McGraw-Hill, Jones &amp; Bartlett, Course Technology, and dozens <ulink
    role="orm:hideurl"
    url="http://www.safaribooksonline.com/publishers">more</ulink>. For more
    information about Safari Books Online, please visit us <ulink
    role="orm:hideurl"
    url="http://www.safaribooksonline.com/">online</ulink>.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>How to Contact Us</title>

    <para>Please address comments and questions concerning this book to the
    publisher:</para>

    <simplelist type="vert">
      <member>O’Reilly Media, Inc.</member>

      <member>1005 Gravenstein Highway North</member>

      <member>Sebastopol, CA 95472</member>

      <member>800-998-9938 (in the United States or Canada)</member>

      <member>707-829-0515 (international or local)</member>

      <member>707-829-0104 (fax)</member>
    </simplelist>

    <para>We have a web page for this book, where we list errata, examples,
    and any additional information. You can access this page at:</para>

    <simplelist type="vert">
      <member><ulink
      url="http://www.oreilly.com/catalog/&lt;catalog page&gt;"></ulink></member>
    </simplelist>

    <remark>Don’t forget to update the &lt;url&gt; attribute, too.</remark>

    <para>To comment or ask technical questions about this book, send email
    to:</para>

    <simplelist type="vert">
      <member><email>bookquestions@oreilly.com</email></member>
    </simplelist>

    <para>For more information about our books, courses, conferences, and
    news, see our website at <ulink
    url="http://www.oreilly.com"></ulink>.</para>

    <para>Find us on Facebook: <ulink
    url="http://facebook.com/oreilly"></ulink></para>

    <para>Follow us on Twitter: <ulink
    url="http://twitter.com/oreillymedia"></ulink></para>

    <para>Watch us on YouTube: <ulink
    url="http://www.youtube.com/oreillymedia"></ulink></para>
  </sect1>
</preface>